Guide to the National Woman's Party Pamphlet Collection, approximately 1923-1946
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
National Woman's Party Pamphlet Collection
approximately 1923-1946
National Woman's Party
1.2 cubic feet (4 manuscript boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Pamphlets, flyers, congressional reports, clippings issued or collected by the National Woman's Party.
Administrative History
Under the leadership of Alice Paul the National Woman's Party (NWP) emerged in 1916 from the formal union of the Congressional Union for Woman Suffrage and the Woman’s Party. From 1916 to 1920 the NWP worked on the federal level to secure for women the right to vote. After the ratification of the 19th Amendment, the organization began a decades- long campaign to win passage of the Equal Rights Amendment. In addition, the NWP has involved itself in international campaigns for women's rights. In 1997 the NWP ceased to be a lobbying organization and since then has devoted itself primarily to education. During the 1930s and 1940s Alma Lutz (Vassar 1912) was active in the NWP and author of a some of the pamphlets included in this collection.
Scope and Content Note
Pamphlets, flyers, congressional reports, clippings issued or collected by the National Woman's Party.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Lutz, Alma; National Woman's Party
Subjects:
Equal rights amendments--United States; Feminism--United States; Suffrage--United States; Women's rights--United States
Document Types:
Flyers, pamphlets, reports
VCL Categories
Politics; Women's History
Encoding Information
Encoded by Mark Seidl, April-May 2014.
Acquisition Information
The 152 items that form the bulk of this collection were donated by Alma Lutz and cataloged in Dewey. Original acquisition date unknown. Ten further items were added; acquisition date unknown. Transferred from Special Collections Dewey materials April 11, 2014.
Arrangement
At the time of initial acquisition (see Acquisition Information below), the bulk of the collection was recorded in a typed inventory in which the items were numbered consecutively from 1 to 152. The arrangement of this collection follows the inventory. The inventory itself, as well as some additional materials not recorded in it, are placed at the end in folders 153-154, respectively.
Container List
- Box 1
  - James Truslow Adams endorses the Equal Rights amendment, undated (Folder 1.1)
  - Alabama laws discriminating against women, undated (Folder 1.2)
  - The governing board of the American Institute of International Law approves equal rights and names Doris Stevens first woman member, 1931 (Folder 1.3)
  - Are women persons in the Commonwealth of Massachusetts, undated (Folder 1.4)
  - An argument for equal rights by federal amendment, undated (Folder 1.5)
  - Babcock, Caroline Lexow, Unity, undated (Folder 1.6)
  - Bitterman, Helen Robbins, The equal rights amendment, 1940 (Folder 1.7)
  - Bringing state laws into harmony with the federal amendment, undated (Folder 1.8)
  - Brown, Helen Elizabeth, Woman lawyer defends "Equal Rights" amendment, undated (Folder 1.9)
  - Brown, Helen Elizabth, Unequal justice under law: women and the constitution, 1942 (Folder 1.10)
  - Buck, Pear S., Pearl Buck endorses Equal rights amendment, undated (Folder 1.11)
  - Buck, Pear S., Women's place in democracy; Expansion of remarks of Hon. Carl Henshaw in the House of Representatives, 1941 (Folder 1.12)
  - Carter, Anne, comp., Amendment ammunition: notes to be used in the campaign for the Equal rights amendment, 1934 (Folder 1.13)
  - The Closing of occupations to women, undated (Folder 1.14)
  - Compulsory joint income tax returns, undated (Folder 1.15)
  - Delaware laws discriminating against women, undated (Folder 1.16)
  - Do you know that a woman does not have equal control of ..., undated (Folder 1.17)
  - Do you know that a woman does not have equal opportunities ..., undated (Folder 1.18)
  - Do you know that a woman does not have equal pay for equal work ..., undated (Folder 1.19)
  - Dock, Lavinia L., Letter to nurses, 1923 (Folder 1.20)
  - The English woman's campaign for legal equality, undated (Folder 1.21)
  - Equal rights, v.22 n.11, June 1, 1936 (Folder 1.22)
  - Equal rights: use equal rights seals ..., undated (Folder 1.23)
  - Equal rights: hearing before a subcommittee of the Committee on the Judiciary, United States Senate ..., 1931 (Folder 1.24)
  - Equal rights for men and women: hearing before a subcommittee of the Committee on the Judiciary, United States Senate ..., 1933 (Folder 1.25)
  - To amend married persons' clause ..., 1935 (Folder 1.26)
  - Equal rights for men and women ..., 1938 (Folder 1.27)
  - Equal rights: a memorandum ..., 1941 (Folder 1.28)
  - The equal rights amendment ..., James M. Tunnell, 1941 (Folder 1.29)
  - Equal rights and conscription, undated (Folder 1.30)
  - The equal rights amendment and protective legislation, undated (Folder 1.31)
  - The equal rights amendment and special laws for working women, undated (Folder 1.32)
  - Equal rights by national amendment, undated (Folder 1.33)
  - The equal rights amendment: the practical solution, 1937 (Folder 1.34)
  - Equal rights by national amendment, 1929 (Folder 1.35)
  - Equal rights by national amendment is more permanent than by state legislation, undated (Folder 1.36)
  - Equal rights for women doctors ..., undated (Folder 1.37)
  - Equal rights or human rights, 1935 (Folder 1.38)
  - "Equal rights" versus sex disqualification removal, undated (Folder 1.39)
  - Equality bills, undated (Folder 1.40)
- Box 2
  - Equality of opportunity, circa 1934 (Folder 2.41)
  - Facts about the National Woman's Party, circa 1924 (Folder 2.42)
  - Facts bout wage earning women, undated (Folder 2.43)
  - A few facts bout the National Woman's Party, undated (Folder 2.44)
  - A few facts bout the National Woman's Party, February 1, 1938 (Folder 2.45)
  - Florida laws discriminating against women, undated (Folder 2.46)
  - Forsyth, Margaret E., Section 213, 1936 (Folder 2.47)
  - Gale, Zona, What women won in Wisconsin, undated (Folder 2.48)
  - Government Workers' Council, Progress report ..., 1935 (Folder 2.49)
  - Greathouse, Rebekah S., Constitutional rights of women, 1935 (Folder 2.50)
  - Hepbron, James M., Women on juries, undated (Folder 2.51)
  - Hepburn, Katherine, Katherine Hepburn endorses the Equal rights amendment, undated (Folder 2.52)
  - The History of Section 213, 1935 (Folder 2.53)
  - Hooker, Edith Houghton, Beware of the "Women's Charter,", 1937; [2 copies] (Folder 2.54)
  - How Colorado laws discriminate against women, undated (Folder 2.55)
  - How long will women wait for liberty? 1848-1922, circa 1924 (Folder 2.56)
  - How long will women wait for liberty? 1848-1937, undated (Folder 2.57)
  - How Maryland laws discriminate against women, undated (Folder 2.58)
  - How Maryland laws discriminate against women, 1922 (Folder 2.59)
  - How Mississippi laws discriminate against women, 1922 (Folder 2.60)
  - How Mississippi laws discriminate against women, undated (Folder 2.61)
  - How New York laws discriminate against women (including changes made in 1922 legislature (Folder 2.62)
  - How New York laws discriminate against women (including changes made in 1923 legislature (Folder 2.63)
  - How New York laws discriminate against women (including changes made in 1924 legislature (Folder 2.64)
  - How New York laws discriminate against women (including changes made in 1925 legislature (Folder 2.65)
  - How New York laws discriminate against women, 1924 (Folder 2.66)
  - How Texas laws discriminate against women, 1926 (Folder 2.67)
  - How the Woman's rights bill works in Wisconsin, 1922 (Folder 2.68)
  - How the Woman's rights bill works in Wisconsin, 1922 (Folder 2.69)
  - How Virginia laws discriminate against women, undated (Folder 2.70)
  - How Virginia laws discriminate against women, 1922 (Folder 2.71)
  - Join the Woman's party, work for the Equal rights amendment, undated (Folder 2.72)
  - Legislation won in the Equal rights campaign, 1921-1929, undated (Folder 2.73)
  - Longer hours for women?, undated (Folder 2.74)
  - Louisiana laws discriminating against women, undated (Folder 2.75)
  - The Lucretia Mott amendment ... pro and con, undated (Folder 2.76)
  - Lutz, Alma, The case for women jurors, circa 1934 (Folder 2.77)
  - Lutz, Alma, Equal rights treaty vs. the Woman's charter, circa 1937 (Folder 2.78)
  - Lutz, Alma, Freedom for women throughout the world, undated (Folder 2.79)
  - Lutz, Alma, Protective legislation for women, yesterday and today, undated (Folder 2.80)
- Box 3
  - Lutz, Alma, Shall woman's work be regulated by law?, circa 1930 (Folder 3.81)
  - Lutz, Alma, There is a tide in the affairs of women, undated (Folder 3.82)
  - Lutz, Alma, What price marriage?, circa 1934 (Folder 3.83)
  - Lutz, Alma, Why discharge women first?, undated (Folder 3.84)
  - Lutz, Alma, Women and wages, circa 1934 (Folder 3.85)
  - Matthews, Burnita Shelton, The denial of justice to women, undated (Folder 3.86)
  - Matthews, Burnita Shelton, The Equal rights amendment, 1934 (Folder 3.87)
  - Matthews, Burnita Shelton, Equal rights versus sex disqualification removal, undated (Folder 3.88)
  - Matthews, Burnita Shelton, Glimpse of laws shows need for equal rights, undated (Folder 3.89)
  - Matthews, Burnita Shelton, Legal status of women in the District of Columbia, 1934 (Folder 3.90)
  - Matthews, Burnita Shelton, The status of women as jurors, 1930 (Folder 3.91)
  - The menace of the interstate compact, circa 1934 (Folder 3.92)
  - Minimum wage legislation which does not apply equally ..., undated (Folder 3.93)
  - Missouri laws discriminating against women, 1922 (Folder 3.94)
  - Missouri laws discriminating against women, 1922 (Folder 3.95)
  - Moncure, Dorothy Ashby, The Equal rights amendment in light of the Fair labor standards act, undated (Folder 3.96)
  - The National Woman's Party: what is it, what has it done, what is it doing?, circa 1924 (Folder 3.97)
  - The National woman's party, 1913-1926 (Folder 3.98)
  - National woman's party: declaration of principles ..., 1922; [typescript] (Folder 3.99)
  - National woman's party: declaration of principles ..., 1922 (Folder 3.100)
  - National woman's party: declaration of principles ..., 1922 (Folder 3.101)
  - Nationality of women, [1929?] (Folder 3.102)
  - New York. No. 1123. Int. 977. In Senate, Feb. 23, 1922 ... (Folder 3.103)
  - Night work for women ("The National Woman's part ...), undated (Folder 3.104)
  - Night work for women ("There is now pending ..."), undated (Folder 3.105)
  - Among the organizations endorsing the Equal rights amendment ..., undated (Folder 3.106)
  - Organizations of women (almost entirely wage-earning) on record against restrictive labor laws ..., undated (Folder 3.107)
  - Organizations opposing special "protective" legislation for women, undated (Folder 3.108)
  - Phelps, Editha, Equal rights in European constitutions, undated (Folder 3.109)
  - The ruling of the Supreme Court, undated (Folder 3.110)
  - Schlesinger, Arthur Meier, Arthur Meier Schlesinger ... endorses the Equal rights amendment, undated (Folder 3.111)
  - Scott, James Brown, Equality triumphs, 1934 (Folder 3.112)
  - Scott, James Brown, Nationality, 1930 (Folder 3.113)
  - Significance of Equal rights amendment ..., circa 1937 (Folder 3.114)
  - Labor laws for women on the wane, circa 1931 (Folder 3.115)
  - Special privileges for women, undated (Folder 3.116)
  - The status of women, the barometer of world progress, circa 1938 (Folder 3.117)
  - Swarthout, Gladys, Gladys Swarthout endorses the Equal rights amendment, undated (Folder 3.118)
  - Swing, Raymond Gram, Raymond Gram Swing endorses the Equal rights amendment, undated (Folder 3.119)
  - This is not a fight against minimum wage!, undated (Folder 3.120)
- Box 4
  - Weed, Helena Hill, The New Deal that women want, circa 1934 (Folder 4.121)
  - West, Byron McG., You can't do this to women, undated (Folder 4.122)
  - What every woman ought to know, undated (Folder 4.123)
  - Which method do you choose?, undated (Folder 4.124)
  - Whitney, Josepha, I appeal to women for united support, undated (Folder 4.125)
  - Why a constitutional amendment, undated (Folder 4.126)
  - Why the Equal rights amendment?, undated (Folder 4.127)
  - Why the Equal rights amendment now!, undated (Folder 4.128)
  - Wiley, Anna Kelton, Mandatory joint income tax return, undated (Folder 4.129)
  - Williams, Mary Wilhelmine, A question of title, undated (Folder 4.130)
  - Wives still regarded as property, undated (Folder 4.131)
  - Womanpower's full use on war urged on U.S., undated (Folder 4.132)
  - A Woman's national headquarters facing the Capitol, circa 1924 (Folder 4.133)
  - The Woman's party and the minimum wage for women, undated (Folder 4.134)
  - Women demand that no labor legislation be enacted ..., undated (Folder 1.135)
  - Women's charter atavistic, declared Lavinia Dock, circa 1937 (Folder 4.136)
  - Women's national organizations on record against National woman's party amendment, undated (Folder 4.137)
  - Woolley, Mary E., Dr. Mary E. Woolley ... endorses Equal rights amendment, undated (Folder 4.138)
  - Working women speak, circa 1937 (Folder 4.139)
  - Questions and answers on the Equal rights amendment, September, 1943 (Folder 4.140)
  - Women are not persons; wives are chattels, undated (Folder 4.141)
  - Banning, Margaret Culkin, Margaret Culkin Banning for equal rights, undated (Folder 4.142)
  - Hayes, Helen, Helen Hayes endorses the Equal rights amendment, undated (Folder 4.143)
  - Lutz, Alma, A feminist thinks it over: the blindness of the exceptional women, undated (Folder 4.144)
  - Lutz, Alma, A feminist thinks it over: the protection of the Equal rights amendment, undated (Folder 4.145)
  - Lutz, Alma, A feminist thinks it over: women, your country needs you!, undated (Folder 4.146)
  - Pollitzer, Anita, Letters to The Times: equal rights move favored, 1943 (Folder 4.147)
  - Armstrong, Florence A., Forward into light, 1944 (Folder 4.148)
  - The present campaign for equality of rights for women, 1945 (Folder 4.149)
  - Babcock, Caroline L., Women's post-war jobs linked to Equal rights amendment, 1943 (Folder 4.150)
  - Equality before the law, 1943 (Folder 4.151)
  - Pollizer, Anita, Is the law unfair to women?, circa 1943 (Folder 4.152)
  - Collection inventory, undated; [includes note from Alma Lutz] (Folder 4.153)
  - Additional materials, circa 1938-1946; [pamphlets, flyers, and news articles not included in original collection inventory] (Folder 4.154)